Guide to the Theresa El-Amin Papers, 1960s-2012 RL.00357
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Theresa El-Amin papers
1960s-2012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
El-Amin, Theresa
RL.00357
30.5 Linear Feet
Activist and union organizer who was involved with the Coalition of Labor Union Women, the Service Employees International Union, the Black Radical Congress, the Black Workers for Justice, Jobs with Justice, Solidarity, and the Durham NAACP. El-Amin was also a founding member of the Labor Party and the Southern Anti-Racism Network. Collection includes organizational and subject files from El-Amin's years of activism and organizing in the Service Employees International Union, the Black Radical Congress, the Southern Anti-Racism Network, and numerous other groups and causes. Also includes publications, photographs, videotapes, and correspondence. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Access Restrictions
Access note. Some materials in this collection are fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
Provenance
The Theresa El-Amin Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from Theresa El-Amin in 2010 and 2014.
Biographical Note
Theresa El-Amin started her career as a civil rights activist when she joined the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) in 1965 as a student at Tuskegee University. On her return to Atlanta in summer of 1966, she took a job at the phone company and became active in the Communications Workers of America (CWA). During the 1980s and through the 1990s, she became involved with the Coalition of Labor Union Women (CLUW), the Service Employees International Union (SEIU), and Black Workers for Justice (BWFJ). She continued her labor organizing with Jobs from Justice from 1993-2006 and by serving on the Labor Notes Policy Committee from 2000-2009. She was a founding member of the Labor Party in 1996. Her work with anti-racist organizations has included the Black Radical Congress (1998-2008), the Durham Committee on the Affairs of Black People (1999-2010), the Durham NAACP (2000-2010), and Solidarity, a socialist, feminist and anti-racist organization (1996-present). In 1998, she helped to found the Southern Anti-Racism Network (SARN), which has worked on local issues like the education gap and passing an anti-sweatshop ordinance in the City of Durham. In December 2010, El-Amin relocated to Georgia to take the role of regional organizer to direct SARN activities in Georgia and Alabama.
Collection Overview
The Theresa El-Amin Papers have been divided into series: Organizations and Movements, Subject Files, Conferences, Personal Files and Correspondence, Printed Materials, Photographs and Audiovisual, Black Liberation Historical Documents, Realia, and Oversize Materials. The largest series, Organizations and Movements, features materials from El-Amin's long career as an activist and union organizer with groups such as Black Workers for Justice, the Service Employees International Union, Jobs with Justice, the Green Party of the United States, the NAACP, the Coalition of Labor Union Women, the Black Radical Congress, Solidarity, and the Southern Anti-Racism Network. Other highlights of the Organizations and Movements series include the Black Liberation movement and the Free Mumia Abu-Jamal movement. There are also numerous other groups and movements represented within this series. Contents typically include handouts and fliers from various events; email correspondence; reports and publications from different groups, including some newsletters; and clippings with coverage of different campaigns and activities.
The Subject Files series was largely created by El-Amin, with additional subjects added in processing to account for loose pages in the collection. Topics heavily represented include Muhammad Ahmad, community organizing and its many components, healthcare, South Africa and apartheid, North Carolina, and workplace safety. There are also subject files for several countries, as well as materials about Hurricane Katrina.
The Printed Materials series includes newsletters, magazines, journals, fliers, handouts, and other miscellaneous materials from a wide variety of sources. The first box contains runs of various periodicals, including Forward Motion, In Defense of Marxism, and Labor Notes. These runs are incomplete and represent only a sampling of the publication. The second box of printed materials relates largely to El-Amin's union involvement, and features miscellaneous union publications from the 1980s-2000s. There is a small amount of earlier material, mainly in the Historical Pamphlets folder, which includes publications on desegregation and its impact on unions. The remainder of the series is also largely miscellaneous, with one or two issues of a wide range of newsletters, magazines, or organizational reports.
The small Conferences series contains conference books, fliers, correspondence, and handouts from various conferences El-Amin attended between 1985 and 2010. There is some overlap between this series and the Organizations and Movements series. Another small series is El-Amin's Personal Files and Correspondence, which consists largely of certificates and other remnants of her professional organizing education and career. This series also includes copies of her resumes and a 1997 oral history transcript.
The Photographs and Audiovisual Materials series includes large amounts of loose photographs, labeled by El-Amin, documenting many of the organizations, activities, and events referenced in earlier portions of the collection. It also includes some personal photographs of El-Amin's family and friends. The VHS tapes in this series document a range of protests and issues important to the BWFJ and El-Amin's union organizing.
Articles and pamphlets acquired by El-Amin relating to the Black Panther Party and the Black Liberation movement of the 1960s are included in the Black Liberation Historical Documents series. Highlights include a transcript of Stokely Carmichael, Chairman of SNCC, speaking at the 1966 Berkeley conference on "Black Power and its Challenges." Includes articles on the condition of African Americans by Bayard Rustin, as well as coverage of the Watts riot and recovery of the Watts area. Also includes several issues of Commentary Reports from the 1960s.
The Realia series is largely unsorted, but includes three boxes of t-shirts and one box of buttons and other ephemera collected by El-Amin in her years as an activist.
Finally, the Oversize Materials contains objects withdrawn from their respective series due to their large size. These include Jobs with Justice foam boards and posters.
Race discrimination; Black power -- History -- 20th century; Black nationalism -- History -- 20th century; Solidarity; Social movements; Photographs; Public Schools -- North Carolina -- Durham; Videotapes; Anti-war demonstrations -- Washington (D.C.); Anti-sweatshop movement -- Durham (N.C.); Political activists; Anti-apartheid activists; North Carolina -- Social movements; Labor unions -- Organizing; Labor movement; Black Radical Congress; Abu-Jamal, Mumia; 1199, National Health and Human Service Employee Union; El-Amin, Theresa; Coalition of Labor Union Women (U.S.); Black Workers for Justice; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Labor Party Advocates (U.S.); Jobs with Justice; Greens/Green Party USA; Southern Anti-Racism Network; Service Employees International Union; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People -- Durham Branch (Durham, N.C.)
- Organizations and Movements, 1980s-2010, 9 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Materials in the Organizations and Movements series are from the numerous organizations and unions that El-Amin either organized for or worked with, including the Black Radical Congress, Service Employees International Union and its Organize the South campaign, Solidarity, the Coalition of Labor Union Women, the Southern Anti-Racism Network, the Ella Baker Tour, the Black Workers for Justice, and Jobs with Justice. Also includes materials from the Black Liberation movement and the movement to free Mumia Abu-Jamal. Materials include correspondence, particularly email printouts; fliers and handouts; reports and other printed material about various issues or missions within each organization; pamphlets and booklets; periodicals, including incomplete runs of BWFJ's Justice Speaks, the Solidarity Bulletins, and various SEIU magazines; union contracts; clippings and press coverage; and other miscellaneous loose material. Series has been arranged alphabetically by organization or group.
  A second series in this collection related to the Black Liberation movement is the Black Liberation Historical Documents series, which is described in further detail below. There are also more organization publications and newsletters in the Printed Materials series.
  - AFL-CIO, 1993-1996 (Box 1)
  - AFL-CIO Rhode Island, 1986 (Box 1)
  - AFSCME privitization and welfare publications, 1996 (Box 1)
  - A. Philip Randolph Institute, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Black Liberation, 1970s-2000s, 10 folders (Box 1)
    Includes a wide variety of publications, reports, meeting minutes, notes, and other printed material discussing the Black Liberation movement, its origina, and its activities. Includes articles discussing socialism and communism as they related to the condition of African Americans.
  - Black Radical Congress, 1998-2000s, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Black Radical Congress, National Organizing Conference, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Black Radical Congress conference, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Black Rank and File Exchange, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - Black Solidarity Against the War, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Black Workers For Justice
    - Justice Speaks newsletters, 1987-1994, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Justice Speaks newsletters, 1994-2008, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - J ustice Speaks correspondence and administration, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, miscellaneous, 1982-1990 (Box 2)
    - Telephone numbers (Box 2)
    - Membership (Box 2)
    - National Steering Committee, 1989-1991, 1993-1995, 7 folders (Box 2)
    - Chapter tasks (Box 2)
    - Fact sheets (Box 2)
    - Bills/banking (Box 2)
    - Fliers and reports (Box 2)
    - Organizing Committee, 1983-1985 (Box 2)
    - Schlage Lock, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Independent politics, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Workers Want Fairness Campaign, 1989 and undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Workers schools (Box 2)
    - Retreats, 1991-1992, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Martin Luther King Banquets, 1990-2006, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - NC Occupational Health and Safety project, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Keysville (Ga.), 1990 and undated (Box 2)
    - Rocky Mt. (NC) Undergarment, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - Ina Mae Best tour, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - Raleigh City Workers, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Standard Products plant, Rocky Mt. (NC), 1993 (Box 2)
    - Living Wage Campaign, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Atlanta Olympics, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Other Southern struggles, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - New England solidarity (Box 2)
    - Rhode Island Support Committee, 1991-1993, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Midwest Tour, 1989-1990, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Midwest Tour, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Organize the South, 1989-1997, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Organize the South-Justice for Hamlet, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Organize the South research, 1996-1997, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Organize the South postcards, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Marc Gursky correspondence re: El-Amin's disability leave, 1996 (Box 3)
    - BWFJ/Organize the South dispute, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Campaign to end the Israeli occupation, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Caribbean International Education Committee, 1992-1994 (Box 3)
  - Carolina Interfaith Taskforce on Central America, 1999-2009, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Civil and Human Rights Commission, 1995 and undated (Box 3)
  - Coalition of Black Trade Unionists, 1986-1990, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Coalition of Labor Union Women, 1986-1993, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Coalition of Labor Union Women newsletters, 1988-1993 (Box 3)
  - Coalition of Labor Union Women printed materials, 1992-1993 and undated (Box 3)
  - Direct Action for Rights and Equality, 1991-2001 (Box 3)
  - Democratic Socialists of America, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Durham Committee on the Affairs of Black People, 2001-2007 (Box 3)
  - Durham Congregations, Associations, and Neighborhoods, 2004-2005 (Box 3)
  - Durham County Board of Social Services, 2008 (Box 3)
  - Durham County Cable Advisory Board, 2008 (Box 3)
  - Durham Housing Authority: Health and Public Housing Initiative, 2009 (Box 3)
  - Durham Public Education Network, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Durham Public Schools
    - Closing the Achievement Gap, 2000-2008 (Box 4)
    - Education and testing, 2000s (Box 4)
  - Ella Baker Tour and retreats, 2000-2010, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Farm Labor Organizing Committee, 1998 (Box 4)
  - Freightliner Five, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Green Party of the United States
    - Triangle Green Party events, 2008 (Box 4)
    - Cynthia McKinney campaign, 2008 (Box 4)
    - Convention, 2008 (Box 4)
    - Black Caucus, 2008 (Box 4)
    - NC Green Party meetings, 2009-2010 (Box 4)
    - Annual meetings, 2009-2010, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 2010 (Box 4)
  - Heirs to a Fighting Tradition, 2006-2008 (Box 4)
  - Highlander Research and Education Center, 1998-1999 (Box 4)
  - Jobs with Justice
    - JWJ materials, 1993-2000s (Box 4)
    - National office materials, including correspondence, 1993-2000s (Box 4)
    - Comic about welfare, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Religions clippings, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Workers rights and economic justice resource book, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Newsletters, 1997-2002 (Box 4)
    - Clippings and publicity, 1997-2000, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Regional materials, 1994-2002 and undated (Box 4)
    - Triangle JWJ materials, 2000-2005 (Box 4)
    - Anti-sweatshop campaigns, 2000-2007, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Building Jobs with Justice reference binder, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - National Day of Action, 1997 (Box 5)
  - Labor Notes materials, 1999-2001 (Box 5)
  - Labor Party, 1996-2001 (Box 5)
  - Labor Party Advocates, 1991-1996, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Labor for Jesse Jackson campaign materials and coverage, 1988-1991, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Living Wage Campaign, 1998 and undated (Box 5)
  - Martin Luther King Coalition meetings, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Mumia Abu Jamal
    - Correspondence, 1991-1999 and undated (Box 5)
    - Protests and rallies, 1990-2000s, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Articles and reports, 1989-2000s, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - 2 audiocassettes (Box 5)
  - NAACP, 2004-2005 (Box 5)
  - NAACP Legislative Day, NC, 2010 (Box 5)
  - NAACP Mark Stanton Curtis case, 1988-1991 and undated (Box 5)
  - National Organization for Women, 2007 (Box 5)
  - National Organizers Alliance, 2001-2007 (Box 5)
  - 1199/NEHCEU
    - Materials and correspondence, 1989-1993 (Box 5)
    - NHHSEU Union contracts, 1988-1991 and undated (Box 5)
    - Newsletters, 1991-1993 (Box 5)
  - New Voice, 1995 (Box 5)
  - NC Coalition Against Domestic Violence, 2008-2010 (Box 5)
  - Northeast Ohio Anti-Apartheid Committee, including clippings, 1986-1989 (Box 6)
  - Oppressed Nationalities Alliance for Cooperation and Progress, Malcolm X materials, 1990 and undated (Box 6)
  - Oppressed Nationalities Alliance for Cooperation and Progress, notes and meeting minutes, 1990-1991 (Box 6)
  - People First! Budget Coalition, 1992-1993 (Box 6)
  - People of Color, 2005 (Box 6)
  - Rhode Island Women's Health Collective, Board information and newsletters, 1991-1993 (Box 6)
  - Rhode Island Working Women, 1993-1994 (Box 6)
  - Service Employees International Union
    - ACC Clerk Petition (Box 6)
    - AFL-SEIU News, 1991-1995 (Box 6)
    - African American Caucus, 1993-1996, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - African American Leadership Conference, 1996 (Box 6)
    - Bargaining agreements, Union of Unions, 1991-1995 (Box 6)
    - Blue Cross/Blue Shield organizing, undated (Box 6)
    - Brown University organizing, 1988-1991, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Reports from the Committee on the Future, 1994 (Box 6)
    - Contracts, 1989-1994 (Box 6)
    - Convention reports, 1996, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 6)
    - Eastern Union Skills Program, 1994 (Box 6)
    - Healthcare bargaining, 1986 (Box 6)
    - Healthcare reform, 1990-1995, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Healthcare worker publications, 1995 (Box 7)
    - Homecare works, 1995 (Box 7)
    - Inclusion: A Tool for Organizational Effectiveness, 1996 (Box 7)
    - Local 285, annual convention, 1994 (Box 7)
    - Local 285 New Members Kit (Box 7)
    - Local Union Organizers conference, 1996 (Box 7)
    - Magazines and publications, 1988-1995, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous documents (Box 7)
    - New Voices (Box 7)
    - Nurse Staffing Kit and nurse-related publications (Box 7)
    - Organizing plans, 1989-1991 and undated (Box 7)
    - Organize the South, 1996 (Box 7)
    - Public Division Bargaining Conference, 1994 July (Box 7)
    - South African Freedom Fund, 1988-1991 (Box 7)
    - Staff training, 1991 and undated (Box 7)
    - Supervision, 1995-1997 (Box 7)
    - Union contracts, 1983-1997, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Update and other publications, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Share the Wealth, 1995 (Box 7)
  - Solidarity (Box 8)
    - Working papers and correspondence, 1999-2009 and undated (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 2004 (Box 8)
    - Timeline notes, undated (Box 8)
    - Pre-convention Bulletin, 2004 (Box 8)
    - Resources (Box 8)
    - Clark Atlanta University travel, 2004 (Box 8)
    - Summer School, 2006-2008, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Bulletins, 1997-2008, 8 folders (Box 8)
  - Staff unionism (Union of Unions) (Box 8)
  - Southern Anti-Racism Network, 1999-2010
    - SARN materials and correspondence, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Anniversaries, 2004-2010 (Box 8)
    - Labor Notes/Day School, 2000, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Highlander program, 1999 (Box 8)
    - Budgets, 2000 (Box 8)
    - Receipts, 2000 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 8)
    - SARN-Durham Housing Authority, 2001 (Box 8)
    - Strong Parental Involvement in Community Education, 2005-2007, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - SARN Expansion Celebration, 2010 (Box 8)
  - Southerners for Economic Justice, 1998 (Box 8)
  - TransAfrica anti-apartheid materials, 1986-1988 (Box 9)
  - TWU Local 100, 1998 and undated (Box 9)
  - Union Baptist Church, 2004-2010, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - United States Out of the Middle East Coalition, 1990-1992, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - United States Social Forum, 2007 (Box 9)
  - Women In Leadership Development
    - Board materials, 1995 and undated (Box 9)
    - Summer Institute for Union Women/Working Women materials, 1992-1995 (Box 9)
    - Popular Education, 1995 and undated (Box 9)
    - Curricula, 1997-1998 (Box 9)
    - Planning, 1997 (Box 9)
  - Work First, 1998 (Box 9)
  - Workers Unity Network, 1991-1996, 2 folders (Box 9)
- Subject Files, 1980s-2010 and undated, 3 boxes
  The Subject Files series was largely created by El-Amin, with additional subjects added in processing to account for loose pages in the collection. Topics heavily represented include Muhammad Ahmad, community organizing and its many components, healthcare, South Africa and apartheid, North Carolina, and workplace safety. There are also subject files for several countries, as well as materials about Hurricane Katrina.
  While there is some overlap between the Subject Files and the Organizations and Movements series, the Subject Files are generally more generic information about a movement or topic, whereas the Organizations series highlights El-Amin's involvement in a particular group or protest. Subjects have been arranged alphabetically.
  - Affirmative action, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Muhammad Ahmad, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Alternate roots, 2004-2005 (Box 10)
  - Angola (Box 10)
  - Anti-Apartheid (Box 10)
  - Anti-Racism (Conference on Whiteness) (Box 10)
  - Anti-Union (Box 10)
  - Anti-War (Box 10)
  - Art of Listening (Box 10)
  - Black history (Box 10)
  - Black-Jewish relations (Box 10)
  - Black radicals (Box 10)
  - The Blackman's Guide... essays, 1990 (Box 10)
  - Campaign planning (Box 10)
  - Cape Verde (Box 10)
  - Collective bargaining, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Community (Box 10)
  - Consultant letters (Box 10)
  - Contingent worker equity campaign, 1997 (Box 11)
  - Corporation for Enterprise Development publications, 1994 (Box 11)
  - Criminalization/prisons (Box 11)
  - Crown boycott, 1996 (Box 11)
  - Cuba (Box 11)
  - Cuba, Mexico, and Central America (Box 11)
  - Cultural (Box 11)
  - Durham politics (Box 11)
  - Education (Box 11)
  - Fair pay/equity (Box 11)
  - Free Trade agreements (Box 11)
  - Grace Lee Boggs Center, 2007 (Box 11)
  - Grants (Box 11)
  - Grievance handling (Box 11)
  - Haiti (Box 11)
  - Fred Ho (Box 11)
  - Hospital organizing (Box 11)
  - House calls (Box 11)
  - Human rights (Box 11)
  - Immigrant rights (Box 11)
  - Immigration (Box 11)
  - Impasse (Box 11)
  - Internal organizing (Box 11)
  - Healthcare, 1993-1994 (Box 11)
  - Hurricane Katrina, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Ku Klux Klan (Box 11)
  - Jobs and development (Box 11)
  - Labor notes and factsheets (Box 11)
  - Labor studies, 1989 (Box 11)
  - Leadership deveopment (Box 11)
  - Legal notices (Box 11)
  - Liberia (Box 11)
  - Samora Machel--Mozambique (Box 11)
  - Malcolm X (Box 11)
  - Martin Luther King Jr. speeches (Box 11)
  - Media (Box 11)
  - Million Man March, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - NAACP, 2007 and undated (Box 11)
  - National Judicial Education Program--Sexual Violence (Box 11)
  - National Labor Relations Board (Box 11)
  - Needlestick Prevention Factbook (Box 11)
  - North Carolina nonprofits (Box 11)
  - North Carolina politics (Box 11)
  - North Carolina public equal employment law (Box 11)
  - North Carolina public workers (Box 11)
  - North Carolina Pride, 1999-2000 (Box 12)
  - Occupational exposure to bloodborne pathogens (Box 12)
  - Ohio Black Trades, 1994 (Box 12)
  - Organizing model (Box 12)
  - Palestine (Box 12)
  - Parents group (Box 12)
  - Plant closings (Box 12)
  - Police brutality (Box 12)
  - Privatization (Box 12)
  - Public Sector Law notes, 1995 (Box 12)
  - Racism (Box 12)
  - Resource materials (Box 12)
  - Resumes (not El-Amin's) (Box 12)
  - Rhode Island TV Soapbox (Box 12)
  - Saladin Muhammad/ACTWU (Box 12)
  - Self-Sufficiency Standard, 1996 (Box 12)
  - Sexual harassment (Box 12)
  - Steward training (Box 12)
  - Striker replacement (Box 12)
  - Student-Labor (Box 12)
  - United Nations/human rights (Box 12)
  - United States Social Forum (Box 12)
  - Universal healthcare (Box 12)
  - Welfare laws (Box 12)
  - Welfare reform (Box 12)
  - Wheat Street Towers Association (Box 12)
  - Witness for the Dead delegation to Colombia, 2002 (Box 12)
  - Women's health (Box 12)
  - Women's liberation/feminism (Box 12)
  - Worker resources (Box 12)
  - Workplace organizing (Box 12)
  - Workplace safety (Box 12)
  - Writing (Box 12)
- Printed Materials, 1978-2010 and undated, 3 boxes